profiles in holography is brought to you
through the generous support of the
international holography fund for more
information visit their website at
holographyfund.org
hello everyone this is Frank de Freitas
and I would like to welcome you to the
2008-2009 season opener for the holotalk
show the internet radio broadcast for
lasers and holography here at
holoworld.com now on its 12th year I
believe or 13.
I do not remember any longer how long
it's been
my guest this week for this opening show
is Anna Maria Nicholson who is the
founding director of the center for
holographic Arts in Long Island City New
York and Anna is going to tell us
amazing stories about her Beginnings in
holography back when they were next door
neighbors to Lloyd cross and the early
days and moving on up to the founding of
the center before we get started with
Anna Maria I would like to also welcome
you to stop by a new section of my own
website which is called antiquarian
holographica now let me tell you briefly
what that means about 20 years ago 20
years ago exactly
I wrote an article entitled antiquarian
holographica and it was an article about
collecting holographic memorabilia or
what they term printed ephemera and
ephemera is materials that have a very
short lifetime for instance if you get a
postcard in the mail that says that so
and so is having an exhibit that's
running from August such to November
such
that is considered ephemera because you
look at that and you don't save it you
throw it away well I saved everything
and because this is the 20th anniversary
of that article I thought you know what
it's time to crack open the archives and
that's exactly what I did this past
summer
and I found thousands
thousands of pieces of holographic
history
in my filing cabinets that is currently
being archived and entered into a
searchable database so that's a new
section of the website every Monday
Wednesday and Friday I put up a new
piece of holographic ephemera for you to
take a look at and to even hear a little
bit of a story behind each one of the
pieces because I didn't buy them on eBay
I actually got them in real time and
they go back over 32
years so I've been collecting these
pieces for 32 years
so hopefully one day when I pass on I
I'm going to have it designated that
this collection be turned over to an
appropriate in tuition or organization
that will take care of it
for people in the future to be able to
see this work now some of the pieces
have Holograms but the majority of the
pieces do not
and that's what's important because a
lot of times people saved
pieces that had holograms on them but
they threw away
the pieces that did not have Holograms
and my collection was heavily focused on
printed ephemera whether it had a
hologram or not so I'm imagining that
some of the pieces some of them
may be the only existing pieces left in
the world of these particular pieces of
paper
thousands of them so antiquarian
holographica if you go to holowworld.com
you'll see a link that'll take you over
and every Monday and Wednesday Friday
you'll see a a new piece put up and a
little bit of a story behind the piece
and you'll be able to take a look at the
collection so without further Ado let's
move on to my interview with Anna Maria
Nicholson
and I'd also like to point out there's a
little bit of a hum
that got picked up by the recording I'm
trying to find out what that hum is I
cannot find it it's not here now but it
was there doing the recording
just goes to show but anyway I don't
think it's that obtrusive that it's
going to take away your pleasure of
listening to the fascinating stories
that she's going to tell you tonight on
whole talk so this is Frank de Freitas
thank you for listening and I look
forward to having you come back for
further Holo talk shows over the winter
months if you happen to be in the
Northern Hemisphere and the lucky ones
the summer months if you're in the
southern hemisphere all right take care
hello Martina how are you it's Frank de
Freitas
doing good
yes I am
yeah I'll pass you over thank you so
much hi hello how are you
are you uh ready to do our little
interview
well I'm sure that the world's ready to
hear from you too
oh I'm sure the people are going to love
to hear everything about what you've
done photography what an impressive life
and career you've had
and it's still in such the early days
too well
okay well let's let's start off the
interview by having you tell a little
bit about your early history in
holography
and the work that you and your husband
were working on and then we'll just take
it step by step finally leading up to
the Center for holographic arts in Long
Island City New York okay so first off
what brought you to holography in the
first place okay what happened was that
uh by chat Peter and I had were became
quite interested in holography uh just
the idea of it you know it was
everywhere remember the Life magazine
article and all of that yes yes and by
chance uh Lloyd cross
rented for this uh for the summer the
love behind us on Prince Street oh no
kidding yes and we met you know on the
street he helped us unload the car one
day and he had all of these Holograms he
had done at the University of where he
was when he now was presenting them to
the world okay and he that's where he
started doing the laser he
for laser light shows yeah
the very early laser relationship very
early yeah and one of the first ones was
done in our building on Prince Street oh
no kidding yeah and what were you doing
at the time
I was a mom and okay doing photography
you know and I was I've always dabbled
but uh when then I saw a hologram of
several of the Holograms that Lloyd had
and it was just absolutely
what type of holograms did he have were
they were they the multiplex Holograms
yet or just just very simple reflection
or laser transmission there were no
reflection then he was laser illuminated
okay
transmission okay wow you remember when
you see that your first hologram oh
absolutely yeah so I thought this is
this is what I need to do with my life
and
so many people tell the same thing I
wonder what happened
you know
esoterically they say that we all come
from uh we all came from Atlantis where
we were all involved in holography oh
okay yeah
couldn't go for that better than coming
from Philadelphia where I came from
so then
um uh Lloyd cross and and Peter and I uh
and our families we went to Arizona
to a school called Verde Valley School
where a friend of mine was teaching and
they started a holography program it was
a high school oh and um so that's where
alloy cross invented uh the multiplex no
kidding yes what a wonderful fascinating
story this is
and uh so after after that we all went
to San Francisco where he
school
and we kind of split from there Peter
and and Lloyd had a big disagreement on
on what the future of holography was
going to be oh
and Peter thought that we should
concentrate on pulse philosophy okay and
and Lloyd was saying continuous wave I
would imagine well Multiplex Multiplex
and so which
we all both felt that it wasn't the real
holography you know
and then uh after that we came back to
New York and we Peter got a grant from
the the Kaplan fund to
uh to organize an exhibition of
holography for the
biennial bicentennial
uh celebrations
and he went around the country and he
realized by that time that the lord of
the um
this facilities were closing
you remember that that period what are
you talking about 76 I would imagine
right yeah
yeah when uh you know all that easy
money that people dreamed of didn't
materialize so he convinced uh McDonnell
Douglas to donate
some of his equipment
he went to the Smithsonian and and
convinced them to start a holography
program
and um and the kaplan's funded it and
the there was equipment from McDonald
Douglas was that at the Cooper Hewitt
Museum that program he was it was the
Cooper Hewitt was part of this before
okay yeah
yeah and then
um we found space at Brookhaven National
Laboratory those were the days
and so we had the program there
for three years okay
and it was the center for experimental
holography
and at the end of that that period we
the University of Hawaii was very
interested in starting new non-polluting
uh
Technologies
so we went to the University of Hawaii
before
experimental holography and that's where
we did the portrait of
Arnold Schwarzenegger which I have which
we just transferred to and it looks
great so and then after that the
funding stopped so we had we formed a
commercial company called holographics
okay where was that located uh it was it
started in Hawaii but we came then back
to New York New York okay and it was in
and then
the basically that most of the energy of
the company was for non-destructive
testing I see and that's when
a small laser affordable pulse laser uh
and I then took over the whole
portraiture and my own art Holograms and
eventually
reporter Studio at the Museum of
holography yeah you also had a show at
the Museum of Photography right yes
and then I went the museum closed
um there was you know nothing nothing in
New York as you know and
um
in 19 I started working with Dan
Schweitzer he came to help me I had to
show them at the Fishback gallery on
57th Street not familiar with that but
it was a it was a good gallery Now isn't
in Chelsea but then he was in 157th
Street and I needed help and then came
to help me to put together the
exhibition and
um
we met
Posey Jackson and the uh
um he thought that they had to have a
new center for holography was a very
good idea and that Sultan and I were we
got along so well and you know how
wonderful Dan was oh yeah absolutely
um and then so we got funding from the
at that time with the Shearwater
Foundation
and they very very
generously
seriously funded us the first three
years and you're celebrating your 10th
anniversary we are celebrating our 10th
anniversary as of August
um is that correct no the August is
going to be the 11th August well this
past August
10th yes and um the equipment
um I
the holographic so the company I was
working for
um I was bought by some German company
and they weren't interested in in the
whole portraiture or or
holography and so I they owed me quite a
bit of back pay so instead uh they gave
me all the the false laser and all that
yes that's a nice deal it was a very
nice deal
sometimes happens when these companies
change they just throw things out oh
absolutely
I'm finding that out with a lot of
materials
I mean it was horrible no what happened
to Paul well I from what I understand
they just even even
access plate anything they just it was
they were on uh on the on the dumpsters
that's horrible I know I know but so
anyway I was very we were very lucky and
we started the center for the
holographic card now I've I've seen your
portraiture for years
and when I was up at the center visiting
last time I wanted to try and figure out
uh exactly
what it was about your work that made it
so different to me
viewing it that uh and I think the word
that I was looking for I couldn't find
the word at the time but I think the
word is that everyone looks more human
in your work than
a post work that I've seen
well you know forfeiture is an art form
and a very ancient art form when it
comes to that
so it's not that just anyone can take a
good pull I mean anyone can take a
portrait but to take a really good
portrait takes a little bit of finesse
you know and our artistic uh
lighting technique
Community the last thing is it's
standard for what post work would be
right or yes because when we were at the
Museum we only had one light
on for for the portrait when we came to
the center we decided to that we needed
to be more flexible so we now have two
lights uh the light from both sides of
the face
um but that's not where it you know why
they look so different I think that is
because you need to establish a
relationship
and see where they are and who they are
also don't forget that they are it's a
very intimate situation because you're
in the dark yes
yes they've never been through this
experience yes it's a laser that's going
to flash on them they don't know what's
going to happen to them exactly so I
think that they're more vulnerable and
more open and they then is that
that gives you the opportunity to
establish this rapport with with your
client and why don't you tell the
listeners some of the people who you
have
created holographic
four yes well
hi Schwarzenegger
um if I can remember everyone
um Walter Cronkite
baby Byrne of the talking head uh
uh helped me here Gloria Steinem Gloria
Steinem
um
Keith herring Keith Haring Philip
Johnson
Diane Dixon
Olympic Athlete yeah I did I had I did a
series of the Olympians it was called oh
and I
and I'm Diane Dixon and uh Willie Banks
was another one and several others
now the center for holographic Arts is
both
holographic portrait studio and also a
center of learning and an exhibit
Gallery all rolled up into one isn't it
well before we finish with the portraits
I should say that I'm having this
exhibition of portraiture at the butler
Museum in in Ohio and what are the dates
for that November 23rd is the opening
okay and so it'll be it will be very
they are a wonderful uh institution so
that's not Thanksgiving day is it oh
gosh
I doubt it would be yeah me too but
that's that's the takeaway we put it
anyway well it would be Thanksgiving uh
over there anyway
that's something to do after you have
dinner yes let's go over and see the uh
pornographic portrait exhibit exactly it
is on a Sunday how is it on a Sunday
okay
so the center basically uh was
established for two purposes one is to
promote the art of philosophy
to have exhibition s of of art that has
been produced they have been produced
here art pieces the second is the artist
in Residency program where we offer
artists not only not just holographers
but artists of any media to come and
work in explore holography as a possible
art media that's wonderful
and we've had almost close to 50 artists
now okay
um and there are a lot producing many
many many pieces that have been shown
all over the world are you in run
s programs in conjunction with any of
the colleges in New York at all art
schools or anything it's all
independence SBA
Samurai who of course is an integral
part of the center
um
course our SBA course on holography okay
and they come to the center wonderful
yes
we have
other
classes who
will visit and so on and you have a
wonderful lab there we have a wonderful
lab we have a very sweet
sweet sir and we have a good transfer a
table and we have Martina gov uses
helping us here and
bringing in the youth
energy that we used to have
yes
I still have it
let the world know I still have it
sometimes in the middle of the night you
say oh my God I know I know but it's a
magical
my magical absolutely once you're
involved with it that's it you're stuck
exactly I think for most people although
the more I go through my historical
records and materials here and archive
them the more our names come up
about how long
or more with so
they come Indigo and but we do have
enough young people coming in that's
good
not if not like in the old days where
everyone had their own little
lamb you remember but now
um I don't know I think that there is a
it's a lot of curiosity and interest and
of course whenever we have exhibitions
people just love the meeting what are
some of the programs that you have
coming up there on your calendar
anything that you can mention
well we have an exhibition by you young
Ali of Korea okay
okay then uh which is opening uh next
month then we have an exhibition uh Sam
Morris having an exhibition uh at the
end of the year okay Martin
foreign
we had an exhibition of collaborations
that really worked out and I had done
many years ago and now
and I will see them again
I just found one of the original
exhibit catalogs from Sam Murray at the
Museum of holography from 1980
. oh my goodness yep that was that's
great I found that
well these episodes are very very very
fine artist and hopefully and I you know
it'll be a great show
I'm sure it will be
for beautiful work yeah so you know we
are
um very we are completely dependent on
on grants so
um we're now waiting to hear what kind
of funding we have for next year and if
anyone ever wanted to learn how to do
holography they can just contact you for
your Workshop programs as well
absolutely they should go through our
website Absolutely I'll have a link to
your website as well oh great yeah but
tell everyone what it is in case you're
listening to this 10 years later
hollow center that
and.com
and it's uh there we have all the news
we are doing what we're doing and also
what other holographers around the world
are doing and we have we post
dates for the workshop
and it's still very exciting work that
you're doing there
well thank you that never ends and and I
love coming in I've been into the center
of the center several times now I don't
get into New York as much as I used to
when I was younger the trip takes a lot
out of me when I came back from that
trip my wife and I took out there
remember we were tired what a Charming
wife you have oh thank you so much
you're so lucky I
am yes lucky for somebody like me I'm
lucky
I'm so supportive of your endeavors yeah
yeah well
sometimes you need to have that in order
to get your
do what it is
they can leave something behind after I
move on to greener
green or Panda well I think that the
work that we have been that we have done
and we're doing still here the pulse I
think that how long is he's going to be
taking a turn towards much more of the
whole Digital World absolutely and but I
think that these pulse
CW work that we've been doing it will be
they will be seen as as the daggerate
are seen now it's very fine pieces of
and you're so special well thank you
yeah absolutely
because I do have a couple portraits
myself here in my own I have a small
collection of holograms nothing like
some people
Jonathan Ross has an enormous collection
of Photography but uh
yours definitely has a more humane
feel to it than the other portrait
portrait that you'd get that many people
who would give that common
remark that the people look waxy or
ghost-like in your Holograms because
they maintain that that feeling of being
present
personality of something internal rather
than just surface well thank you yeah
and it's tough to achieve with anything
and you yeah you know some of my other
work I've done a I'm very very
interested in
it in form and I've done a great many uh
pieces that you know I've had that many
other exhibitions in many different
styles of work as well right yeah and my
the latest one
um I really became very interested in
boring
the same theme with three different
media and I and I did a video and
photography and holography and it was
called um
uh hide and seek
really if you go to my website Anna
Maria
nicholson.com oh I didn't even know you
had a personal web
all these years how long have you had
that
many years I always went to the hollow
center website no no well they are
linked to me but yes and you'll see how
you know a different connections well I
will most definitely make sure that
everyone's aware of that as well thank
you yeah I'm coming in a little at the
end of the line there on
on that a little late
but now it's something for me to do
later tonight
do editing on the audio and I can visit
your website while I do that okay all
right and is there anything else before
we close that you would like the
listeners to know about that I didn't
ask about
well
I don't know we're open to the public uh
on Saturdays for people to come and see
the exhibitions and and we are also they
can call and make a
um if they cannot make it on a Saturday
and
um
that's it that's it and then for more
information visit the website visit the
website okay
okay show it was an honor to interview
and and please say hello to everyone for
me again yes I will thank you so much
for for calling okay take care bye